[Music]
Hey, hey,
hey, hey.
[Music]
Good morning everyone and welcome to
fiber the fiber broadband association's
five for breakfast. We are now in our
35th episode of 2025. Before we kick
off, like to thank Westco and Gaia, the
platinum sponsors of Five for Breakfast
in Washington DC, members of Congress
are going to return next week. And on
Wednesday, September 3rd at 10 a.m.,
this the House Small Business Committee
will hold a full committee hearing
titled Wired for Growth: How expanding
broadband can revitalize small
businesses or real small businesses. So
the fiber broadband associations
welcomes this important discussion
highlighting the small business angle of
fiber broadband deployment is its
economic benefit and look forward to the
uh conversations on broadband's role in
revitalizing rural communities. You know
at NTIA uh the be final proposals are
being published by the states for public
comment ahead of the September 4th
deadline uh with Texas and California
granted extensions. So, what we've seen
so far is West Virginia is awarding 94%
of its locations to fiber. North Dakota
is at 93% fiber. Maine at 85% fiber.
Virginia 81% fiber. Louisiana 80% fiber.
Georgia 76% fiber. Wisconsin 74% fiber.
Arkansas 76 fiber. Oklahoma 65% fiber.
Uh, Pennsylvania, 64% fiber. Colorado is
kind of a strange one. It's u 48% fiber,
2% fixed wireless, and 50%
LEO. Oo, hate to be in Colorado. Um, and
then Kansas is really strange. So, it's
46% fiber and 51% fixed wireless and
fiber. Um, so I'm talking, you know,
Joseph Lee is kind of there's a lot of
fiber in that fixed wireless and fiber.
So, I don't really know what that number
is, but 3% LEO.
So, anyway, we'll see them keep rolling
in. That's kind of all over the map
there. Um, at the FCC, uh, the Fiber
Broadband Associations is preparing to
submit comments in response to the FCC's
annual section 706 notice of inquiry
determine whether advanced
telecommunications capability is being
provided to all Americans in a
reasonable and timely fashion. You know,
I remember back nearly 30 years ago, a
friend of mine, Mark Zance, who's CEO of
Westell at the time, he had these
baseball caps made that had 706 across
the front. And who knew that 30 years
later we'd still be filing our annual 76
comments. So, um, interesting how, uh,
the Telecom Act in 1996, 1996. Um, we'll
see whatever happens here. Um, the Fiber
Broadband Association's regional fiber
connect workshop in Toronto last week
was our best yet. It was just absolutely
amazing. So, I can't wait to our next
regional event in Spokane. U, it's in,
excuse me, Spokane. I looked that up.
Spokane. It's on September 16th. Then
we'll be followed by Scottsdale on
October 16th, Kansas City on November
11th, and then we'll have our premier
member meeting in Palm Springs on
December 8th and 9th. Today on Fire for
Breakfast, our guest is Bri Mackey, the
executive director of the Minnesota
Office of Broadband Development to
discuss best practices when dealing with
bead complexities. Before I formally use
today's guest, I'd like to introduce
David Norris from our team who's going
to walk us through some housekeeping
items.
>> Thank you very much, Gary. And good
morning to everyone who's joined us
today. We appreciate it. Before I go
over a few logistics, we'd like to once
again thank our platinum sponsors of
Fiber for Breakfast, West Co and Gaia.
Now, as participants, you are in
listenon mode today. To ask a question,
please type it into the question tool,
which is located in the lower lefth hand
side of your screen. We will have a Q&A
with our panelist at the end of today's
uh uh discussion. This presentation is
being recorded and will be available on
FDA's website within 24 to 48 hours, and
you can find that recording in the
events tab under the fiber for breakfast
dropown option. Finally, at the
conclusion of today's webinar, you'll be
prompted to complete a brief feedback
survey. Please take a moment to respond.
We appreciate the input. And with that,
I will hand things back over to Gary to
get us started. Gary,
>> thanks, Dave, and good morning. I'm Gary
Bolton, the president CEO of the Fiber
Broadband Association. La last week on
Fore Breakfast, our guest was Ed
Barrett, the president of broadband at
HR Green to discuss grading America's
broadband, the findings of the 2025
report card for America's
infrastructure. You know, Ed shared with
us the American Society of Civil
Engineers first report card on our
nation's broadband infrastructure. So,
spoiler alert, if you missed it, we got
a C++. Uh, but if you missed last week's
session, you can go to the website and
watch the replay. Today in Fiber
Breakfast, our guest is Brie Mackey,
executive director of the Minnesota
Office of Broadband Development Discuss
discuss best practices when dealing with
speed complexity. Uh Bri was appointed
by the Minnesota Governor Tim Waltz in
October 2022 to serve as the executive
director of the Office of Broadband
Development. She previously served as a
senior outreach director and as the
state broadband and telecommunications
director for Minnesota uh US Senator
Tina Smith and prior to for Senator Al
Franklin Franken and she previously
worked as the office administrator for
Winona County Soil and Water
Conservation District. In 2023, she was
appointed to serve on the governor's
infrastructure resiliency advisory
board. In 2024, she was appointed to the
Minnesota Advisory Council on
Infrastructure. Bri currently resides in
Winoa County and is in true form serving
her community in Minnesota. She's the
chair of the uh Lon um Altera School
Board, the chair of the Southeast
Service Cooperative Board and the vice
chair of the Minnesota State Service
Cooperative Board. So, welcome Bri. And
for audience, please type in your
questions as we um walk through our
discussion and we'll work those in. So
with that, let's get things uh started.
So Bri, welcome. You're one of our
favorites. So
>> a that's very kind. Thank you. Well,
Rich, you know, our program director for
our conferences, he is like beside
himself excited about our family feud
that you're going to be on next year at
our conference and uh with the other
state broadband directors. That is going
to be a riot. Um so before we get
started,
chair of the school board,
I can't think of a a more the toughest
job on the planet. You know, I had a
friend who was on the school board in
Texas, and he literally had to have a
police cruiser outside his house at
night that protect him and his family
from parents.
>> Wow.
>> Well, um,
>> things aren't that hard for you on that
school board, but I'm not done.
>> Well, I was on school board during COVID
and and obviously during that time is
very stressful time for all people. And
I think we need to always remember that
the most important thing to anybody is
their children. And so when you're
dealing with parents and and um
teachers, educators all around um
community members, uh if you keep that
in mind that really our interest is the
same to care about our kids and make
sure they get a quality education, um
people just get passionate in different
ways. Um and so that's sort of been my
guiding light. I never thought it'd be
that hard. People always said it was the
hardest. Um, born and raised and stayed
in a community. Our school district's
very small. Um, and it's an opportunity
for me to give back. So, yes,
challenging. Um, but also very proud to
be part of that system.
>> Well, you have a big heart and uh, you
know, hats off and it's I'm sure some
great training for your bead experience.
So
>> fair
>> uh tell us a little bit about um where
you guys are in the process.
>> Yeah. So like every other state
scrambling in these 90 days um we uh did
get the okay yesterday from NTIA during
our special award condition meeting to
move forward uh from NIA. And if
everything falls into place today, as
other state directors know what this is
about, uh everything's fluid and moving.
Uh we're hoping to go out for public
comment tomorrow um and do that for the
seven days and hit our September 4th
deadline. So uh again, a lot of
sleepless nights, uh a lot of trust and
um leaning on the relationships and the
resiliency of our providers and our
community members to stick with us
during this process. Um you know, hats
off to them because, you know, we're
doing the hard work, but they're doing
the commitments. self.
>> Well, you know, we have the greatest
appreciation for you, what the work that
you're doing and your team and all your
colleagues across all 56 states and
territories. We know it was a tough job
before and then the 90 days made it a
little bit tougher, but uh I'm glad that
you guys are finally getting seeing the
light at the end of the tunnel. So, in
June of 2024, so about a year ago, you
had about 74,500
unserved and 46,700
underserved. Um, where did you end up
going into the benefit of the bargain
rounds?
>> Yeah, we ended up at 76,000 about
locations that were eligible for bead
funding.
>> So, that's quite a few less. Did Did you
see what what happened? So, it's kind of
a curveball um that Lutnick threw in
there with this unlicensed um fixed
wireless. How did that impact your
location?
>> Yeah, that certainly did impact our
locations and I I think let's rewind
just for a quick second, Gary. Um one of
the challenging things for the state of
Minnesota is uh the definition of
unserved and underserved and the
statutory language that we carry with
that prior to bead. And so a lot of our
work um upfront and even now is
educating in communities and educating
folks on the difference between what is
eligible for bead and what would be
eligible for our state programs um uh by
definition and we have wire line in our
statutory language. So, it's been very
challenging um in that regard to make
sure that we can kind of
compartmentalize
um those things. And for the average
person who just wants broadband,
reliable uh broadband, including myself
on fixed wireless, um it is challenging
to explain that technically you have it
um by definition with the bead program.
So, um, just wanted to to raise that as
as a as another kind of challenge for a
state of Minnesota. And we're not the
only state. There are other states have
been doing this a long time, but
sometimes that does feel like an extra
barrier in this work because the
expectations are just different.
>> Yeah. I mean, when I talked to Jessica
while back in in Georgia, she's like,
well, the state statute is it has to be
a terrestrial service to be served. And
so when you throw in um these, you know,
LEO or unlicensed wireless and you know,
it's like how do you reconcile what the
state law is versus what we're being
told by these federal programs. So can
you talk a little bit about I mean so
we've had a number of bites of the apple
you know um with uh reconnect and calf
and then um you know we had ARPA and
then um Ardoff um and you whatever other
state monies you had. So kind of can you
walk us through kind of and you know
when I talked to Eric you know he was
talking about how they put a lot of
money into middle mile and things like
that. Was there anything special that
you guys had been kind of working up to
this moment to try to um shore up your
critical broadband infrastructure across
the state?
>> Yeah, I mean the state itself has
invested over 400 million and of course
when we're talking bead dollars, maybe
that doesn't feel like a lot, but for an
individual state to use general fund
money over the past 12 years to fund
this because it is a a priority for the
state um I think is commendable. And um
not only did we develop the
borderto-border grant program um which
provided up to 50% in a subsidy. So
making that business case for providers
to go out in really low dense
communities. Um it has evolved into the
lower population. So then it moved to
the 75% eligible cost because we're
stretching further and further and now
with capital projects dollars we were
able to create the line extension
program. um which really is that last
connection. Um and uh all of them have
been over uh prescribed when we're doing
applications. There is a need out there.
Um but there's also a desire for
internet service providers um to meet
their uh neighbors and customers where
they're at and making sure and ensure
that they have the tools they need um to
be successful wherever they live in the
state. So, um, we were really, um, I
think, uh, right on things with the
capital projects dollars. Um, we worked
really closely with Treasury. We
allocated, uh, we're wrapping up, uh,
projects, um, and and utilizing that
money, uh, as fast as we can, as well as
our state, um, program. Uh, I think this
summer we're on target to uh, close out
53 current grants um, out of our rounds.
And um that's just a testament to not
only are we doing bead, but the state is
continuing to do um what it's invested
in um with other dollars.
>> Well, yeah, I'm glad glad you brought up
um the capital projects fund. So, you
know, Joey Wender and his team of four
got out $10 billion
um pretty quick and you know, we're
coming up on our fourth birthday of the
JA and yet no shovels in the ground. So
can you tell us about of that of the
your capital projects fund what
percentage of those if you were to guess
was fiber projects versus some other
technology?
Well, I think almost all of it
>> 100%.
>> I mean, you know, it so it did run
through our border border grant program.
So, followed those rules and then and
also so, you know, there was additional
speed components and reporting um that
our providers were responsible for doing
um because it was federal dollars. Um
so, meshing those together. Um our
programs are technology technology
agnostic in the state of Minnesota. So
anybody can apply for grants, but you
have to meet the goals and the
requirements of the program on latency
and speed and and all those technical
components. And often we know that that
is fiber in most cases. So um that
program, like I said, we hit the ground
running as fast as we could. Uh
providers were eager to use that that
money and residents were excited to have
that service.
So, what is it about capital pro you and
maybe I'm, you know, you can tell me if
I'm wrong, but it seems like that went
very seamless. The money got out really
quick. You guys were able to deploy and
get to use and got to have a great
outcome. Why did that seem to work so
well yet beads seem so hard?
>> It's a really great question. Um I think
with the capital projects there was an
over sense of urgency because it was co
you know we were people needed they
needed it now and Treasury really took
the approach of getting it to states
fast and states implemented it fast when
they could because they had the
infrastructure and were ready to go and
states that didn't have that
infrastructure uh maybe took a little
bit while longer because this was new to
them. I think, you know, if this is just
Bri talking, but I think with be it is
there's such a pressure to get this
perfect that we're actually forgetting
how potentially easy it could be. And um
again, putting it with the states who
have worked really closely with their
providers, with their communities, with
their lawmakers, all of those things um
you know, perhaps could have streamlined
that. But again, I do think that the the
component of bead that has just been
really challenging is this hope that
it's perfect. And I think we all know um
depending on your state, perfection is
defined in many different ways.
So, okay, prior to June 6th, you had
kind of you were on a certain path and
then when the revisions came down, you
know, I I've heard you um and other
venues talk about that you have less
applications. Kind of tell us kind of
the pre June 6 and post June 6 kind of
what your observations were.
Well, I think first and foremost is is
there's a level of burnout and
confusion. Um, you know, change is hard
even when it's uh, you know, clear. Um,
but then when there's so much
uncertainty, unclearness that that
created um, some chaos and um, for
providers that continue to invest every
day, they're doing it. Communities
continue, small counties are investing
in their providers. Um,
sometimes it's cheaper just to do it
yourself and do it in tanches and know
what's best for your business model um
than it is to take on, you know, a
10-year federal investment and not still
having guidance on what the reporting
requirements may or may not be. Um, and
so just that level uncertainty has
cooled folks off. um you know in in
Minnesota we also with some of those
changes in the policy notice um are
areas that you know we strongly care
about whether it's climate resiliency
whether it's workforce standards um
whether it is opportunities for all
folks um and so I think you know every
state sort of had to look at that and
and our goal is to serve as many people
as we can even with bead if we did you
know every dollar that we can invest in
making sure people have um the type of
broadband um that they deserve is a step
forward. We knew when we started this
652 million as an allocation for
Minnesota was not going to finish the
job based on our statutory language. it
just got a little bit more challenging
with the policy notice um changes and
the way that technology was approached
with this um policy notice.
So, while you know we're not super happy
with um you know how hard it's been for
you guys, um you know, one of the things
the administration did do is on um with
one of the aspects of the big beautiful
one big beautiful bill act was the bonus
depreciation and you know creating much
more free cash flow for service
providers which we're seeing about four
to five billion dollars a year being
plowed into fiber. Are you seeing a
uptick on private investment in fiber in
Minnesota?
>> Um, I think to a degree. Um, I think
it's happening. Like I said, I think
it's always happening. Now, just
remember, my head's been down, working
on beads. So, you know, getting as much
um extras and sort of figuring out where
the state fits in in the next
legislative session, in the next uh
trunch of how we're going to do things
has been a little bit um outside my view
right now. Um but I do know it's
happening. I see it in my own community.
Um you know, I know where there are
state projects and in general federal
projects, so I can tell that there's the
investment happening. Um, and we're
appreciative of that. Um, and we also
know that every move forward and
expansion creates opportunity as it
continues to expand. So, all of that
investment is a good thing. Um, speed is
maybe where those of us or those folks
that don't have um broadband are sitting
here going, I thought I was getting it
four years ago. Um, and that's been sort
of like I said, a challenge to set up
expectations all around. But yes, I
think industry is stepping up and doing
the investments that they can make um
for not only their community but what's
best for their business interests too.
So when you think about
um going forward, so a lot of the states
now have been able to um minimize, you
know, with kind of the focus on the
benefit of the bargain round to focus on
lowest possible costs. Um you know, been
able to come in u well below their
allocation and have what we'll call
non-eployment funds available. given
that you had such a tight budget um and
and what can you say about um what kind
of non-eployment funds you may or may
not have?
>> Yeah, I mean we didn't really allocate
or overconider non-eployment funds at
the start of this because we didn't even
think we'd get to CIS. Um again, we did
a cost data analysis uh private uh and
and had our numbers. We knew based on
line extension and historical data that
I mean if we were going to close and get
everybody as defined in Minnesota, now
let's again separate that out as defined
in Minnesota, it would probably be about
1.2 billion and that's in general fiber
to everybody. Um we do know it doesn't
make sense to get fiber across the river
three miles to a little island. Like we
understand that. Um, but I would just
say like in in the scheme of all of
this, we knew it was going to take a
little bit more. Now, we will
essentially probably have non-deployment
dollars, but we also know these
challenges, challenging locations to
serve are also being hit with uh simple
things like emergency management
connections and how do they access um in
rural Minnesota, their ambulance when
they're in need or um you know, any
other sort of component. So, we're
really trying to look at that. We also
know AI is a huge um thing. In my in my
intro that you were so kind to introduce
me, I'm on a resiliency board. What does
that look like? What does that look like
for broadband and and that that the
infrastructure that we're all building?
So, uh we're looking at it. We don't
have a lot of time to look at it, but we
are definitely looking at it and hope
that we can maximize our request uh to
NTIA. Ultimately, we know in all this
conversation, the decision is up to
them. Um and you know we're hopeful um
and we're doing the best we can for the
states that we serve.
>> Um so two things I you mentioned there.
One um was AI but let me I want to ask
about tribal first. Um you know when we
were just in Alaska um a month ago and
you know they said the golden hour
doesn't exist. you know, when you have
an emergency situation, you know,
getting someone to a hospital within an
hour when you're in the remote reaches
of Alaska just is not possible. You guys
have a similar situation in northern
Minnesota. Um so how do you look at you
know how can you provide emergency
services and be able to have that
critical broadband connectivity whether
it's just remote ultrasounds to you know
emergency things where someone gets
injured uh how was that able to are you
able to com get the infrastructure in
place for that with the bead the bead
money that you have? Well, again, we
definitely are considering it and I I
and I think, you know, though we are not
as remote as Alaska, but even in
Minnesota, I mean, we have cars
topography and and different topography
and landscape across the state, and
there are often spots that there's no
cell service. So, if you don't have even
cell service, and we know landlines have
essentially gone away, you don't have
access to emergency needs. And and I hit
that less than a mile from my home. I
know when I drop down that's how it's
going to be until I get to the next
location where I will have service
again. And and those are real issues.
The other issues which I know is a
little off topic but these small
communities rely on volunteers and so
volunteers need access to making sure
that they can be accessible during a
time of need um when they also live and
work in rural communities across the
state. So, it all falls together. Um,
whether you're the one that needs it and
whether you're the one you're trying to
provide it, you know, access is is
really key. Um, and making sure, you
know, all of the infrastructures are
tied together in a way that can work and
when one doesn't work, the other one can
make sure that it's working as a backup
um is so important.
So can you talk a little bit about your
tribal nations and coordination you did
with the tribes and you know one
opportunity would be is that if you
coupled that with you know um tribal
communities you could reduce or minimize
or get rid of your match. Um did you see
providers that tried to build in some
tribal communities in their proposals
and how'd that work out for you guys?
Yeah, I mean we're again still
evaluating our final numbers, but we had
six of our tribes that had a beat
eligible locations. Um, and I think even
stepping back, you know, we were
required to do consultation based on the
federal guidelines, but in Minnesota,
tribal consultation is a key to any of
the work that we do. Um that is one of
the reasons we were one of the later
states to get our volume 2 approved
because we need to consult with their
tribes even as what is the lowcost plan
that you see fit and reasonable within
your communities. I was not going to
accept that. That is inappropriate and
not the way we do business in Minnesota.
And so we have continued to do that with
them. We will again continue. um NTI did
uh loosen the rules a little bit where
um having tribal consent is not
necessary until the contracting of an
actual project and the locations are
clearly and finalized and identified
which gave us a little room but again we
need to make sure they know what
providers um and then with our borderto
border program and our state programs we
never would fund a project um unless
they had that tribal consent and that
relationship with our tribal partners um
to be able to do that infrastructure
whether it's on or near um those tribal
nations. So this is key and it's just a
foundation of how Minnesota works.
So, you mentioned AI a few minutes ago,
and it seems to me like Minnesota would
be a perfect state to have AI
hyperscalers and AI critical
infrastructure given the access to
water, the land of lakes, and um and
your cool climate and I don't I'm not
sure exactly how your power
infrastructure is, but uh that's a huge
priority for the administration. Um, how
are you guys feeling about your critical
AI infrastructure?
>> Yeah, I mean, I can just speak for for
the office itself, but I think you're
raising really important key components
as far as the state and the um the
resources that we have and the interest
that we have. And yes, I think we have
really key partners. You brought up
Lando Lakes. Um, uh, Teddy Veli is our
chair and he's with Lando Lakes of the
Governor's Broadband Task Force. Uh and
so we uh have great um businesses across
the state that are interested in this
and and will help lead that. You know,
as a state agency, our job is really to
help support those efforts um whether
it's financially or through different
programs, um different tools that maybe
we have, bringing folks together, doing
that partnership. So, we stand ready.
We're interested. Um it's an and also
kind of thing for the office itself, but
really um any of the state agencies are
taking dives into that and really trying
to find out what is the best use of our
resources to be able to support that
expansion and making sure Minnesota can
be a leader in those areas.
Bri, I I wish we had more time because I
always enjoy talking to you and I'm just
so impressed with all the hard work that
you and your team and all your
colleagues across all 56 states and
territories. Just amazing work and uh
you know, we're looking forward to
seeing your draft proposal of tomorrow.
Um I know that you guys work really hard
on that and we hope you guys have the
best possible outcome. Um, I want to
thank everybody for joining us today and
look forward to getting back together
next Wednesday with uh Nick Saparto, the
head of product for Google Fiber, who's
going to be discussing fiber slicing,
unlocking a more open, customized, and
secure experience. So, join us next week
to talk to Google Fiber. Thanks
everyone. Thanks Kimbury.